<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<NewDataSet>
  <VersionData>
    <Version>6.5</Version>
  </VersionData>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>-1</Index>
    <Notes />
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>0</Index>
    <Notes>1 - CREATIVE POWER

The air is ripe with imagination, inspiration and energy. The dragon is an ancient symbol of an electrically charged, dynamic, arousing force that bodes well for creative initiative. If your goals are in alignment with the greater good, your actions will meet with success, but this can only happen if you assert yourself in a positive way. This is a good time to exercise leadership, because you can be strong now. But be forewarned: success turns to failure when strength turns to arrogance.

Believe in your dreams and persevere, and everything around you will flourish. Call upon creative power and let it work through you. Stay focused on your goals; do not let yourself be distracted, or you may lose the power available to you now. And remember that when taking action, success requires good timing.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>1</Index>
    <Notes>2 - THE RECEPTIVE

Great receptivity attracts exceptional results. A natural responsiveness brings about success through support and perseverance, rather than through bold action. Thus, the wise person demonstrates strength like a powerful but gentle mare. This hexagram, consisting of all yin lines, represents a power of the feminine principle no longer honored in our modern world, but such receptivity is most auspicious.

The receptive force is sensual as well as powerful, and it can be missed by too much talk and planning. When spring comes, does the grass "plan" to grow? This is a time to concentrate on realities rather than potentials - with how to respond to a situation rather than how to direct it. The mature mare lets herself be guided by a higher power, and is skilled at graceful acceptance. In a strong spiritual way, her quiet contribution is most effective, and brings success.

Do not be too assertive at this time, for if you try to direct things, you are liable to become confused or alienated. Take your time. Draw strength from carefulness and you will be doubly fortunate. Focus more on feeling than on action. Be broad and deep in your attitudes so that you can accept everything that comes your way with grace and equanimity. Be receptive and spacious like the ocean; let the river of changing developments flow to you. Allow others to take the lead for now. Strive for a pure natural responsiveness that is based on inner strength rather than outer show.
</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>2</Index>
    <Notes>3 - DIFFICULTY AT THE BEGINNING

Difficulty at the beginning. The birth of anything - including any new venture or relationship - is an entry into the realm of the unknown. At the same time, new things seem to be rushing upon you, and confusion can easily take over. But chaos is a powerful force if you harness it properly. Just don't rush things. Do not let events overwhelm you. Stay calm and persevering, but do take the first step. And get whatever help you can.

Challenges lie ahead. Gain strength; find courage. Like a new born fawn, the opportunity for rapid development is real, but only by being determined can the fawn rise to its feet and survive to grow to full stature. Keep going despite difficulties and you will find the success you desire. Your primary challenge is maintaining personal clarity. Avoid lunging at solutions; wait until a good course of action becomes clear. Do not start a new venture before thinking it through. A careless step in the beginning can easily cause events to get out of control later. Enlist the aid of experienced people.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>3</Index>
    <Notes>4 - YOUTHFUL FOLLY

Be on guard for careless or rebellious attitudes characteristic of youthful inexperience. Just as a youth requires instruction, this is a good time to focus on learning your lessons from a patient teacher or life experience. Is there a circumstance in your life, which you have failed to comprehend completely, perhaps because you have failed to appreciate its inherent complexities? Be respectful of anything or anyone who has something to teach you right now.

In order to be ready for challenging times, let education be a continuing part of your life. Be continually developing the strong mind and will necessary to carry one through confusing times. The wise realize that experience, especially difficult experience, is a powerful teacher. But we cannot be forced to learn, even from experience. Be a good student, one who delights in learning, one who nourishes his or her expanding awareness.

Examine your attitude for factors which limit your openness. Observe how you deal with the mistakes of others. You must let people live their own lives and learn their own lessons. Offer others your wisdom or advice, but only if they are receptive. Otherwise, give up trying to convince them that you are right - that is only exhausting and counter-productive. If people are not receptive, let them proceed - even into difficulty or dangerous circumstances. It is the only way they can learn - and without learning, no one can achieve success. This does not mean that you should not care -- just that taking care of someone too much can be harmful. Live and let learn.
</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>4</Index>
    <Notes>5 - PATIENCE

A fisherman can cast the line, but can only wait for the fish to bite. Your catch will come in its own time; you cannot make it come - neither by working nor by planning nor by wishing. You may need to provide nourishment for you and your loved ones; but only through patience can you become the bridge between the fickle fish and the eventual feast. Strength in a time of trial waits quietly, resolutely. Weakness grows agitated, and abandons the effort before the fish bite. Periods of waiting are most fruitful when used for quiet contemplation.

Proceed cautiously, but resolutely, with whatever you are doing. The situation calls for consistency and patience. Waiting is an essential skill; patience is a powerful force. Time is an ally of those with inner strength - the kind of strength which allows you to be uncompromisingly honest with yourself, while sticking to the path you have charted. If you persevere with a positive attitude, time weakens even the hardest obstacles. To rush anything, or impatiently force results, stimulates resistance and causes setbacks. At best, you achieve surface changes that may just as quickly be reversed. Steadfast waiting - holding to your integrity - leads to slow but permanent improvements. In the end, you accomplish something great. Practice patience.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>5</Index>
    <Notes>6 - CONFLICT

Conflict arises when a person who is convinced he or she is entitled to something meets with opposition. In such cases, the wiser choice is not to push things to the bitter end, because knocking heads only perpetuates bad will. Creative solutions which meet others halfway are more valuable and longer lasting than victories achieved through force.

Conflicts in which one party is not sincere inevitably lead to subterfuge and distortions. In such situations, those of strong character keep a clear head, protect their own integrity and look out for their own interests, even while seeking compromise. Often this means finding a fair-minded mediator who can settle matters.

In these times of conflict and turmoil, new ventures and new initiatives are to be avoided.

This is a good time to examine the sincerity of your own beliefs and those around you. Seek advice or arbitration from an impartial and mature person. Consider everything carefully before making any major decisions. It may be time to compromise. Try to clarify the roles and responsibilities of those you work and live with so as to avoid conflict in the future.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>6</Index>
    <Notes>7 - ORGANIZED DISCIPLINE

The most successful general is not the one that triumphs on the battlefield, but the one able, through strength of discipline and inner power, to triumph without spilling blood. Likewise, in any large organization the key virtues are discipline and conscientiousness. The most effective platoon marches with a single purpose - a dedication to a lofty common goal which is held dear by all. Otherwise, even with an excess of external discipline, unpopular wars are seldom winnable.

Let power be held in check by the acceptance of a common discipline, and submission to a higher authority for the common good. When life is in balance, evil impulses are checked by human decency; parents die before their children; leaders lead and followers follow. If you hold or aspire to a position of leadership, remember that the true leader captures the hearts of the people, and articulates a clear, simple vision which binds them together.

In the realm of government, the relationship between the army and state is critical. Only when the state is economically prosperous can the army be strong. Only when the army is disciplined can the state be protected from disruptive outside forces. For this balance to be preserved, government must be steady, and mild toward its own people. When balancing strong complimentary forces, modesty and generosity at the center can be a magnetic force which keeps the relationships intact. Solidarity among all elements is essential for success at this time.
</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>7</Index>
    <Notes>8 - HOLDING TOGETHER

Holding together brings success. But high-level teamwork is achieved only when a clear goal is shared by the right players on the right team at the right time. A team forms its relationships in a delicate manner; chemistry is brewed in the vat of shared experiences. Late-comers cannot share the same depth of union as earlier members. Whole-hearted commitment is required for team success.

All successful teams have a shared vision and a leader. If a team's leadership is up to the challenge, the team will prosper. In political and business affairs, just as in basketball, it is hard to win without a strong center.

Accept the structure of the team if you wish to receive its benefits - otherwise go off on your own. In holding together with others, cling to your own principles, but be willing to subordinate your personal desires for the good of the group. Perhaps you are contemplating becoming a leader of a group; remember that to become the center of influence binding people together is a considerable challenge and a serious responsibility. Assess yourself carefully first to see if you qualify for this role. If not, it would be better that the group not be formed than for you to lead it without proper preparation.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>8</Index>
    <Notes>9 - SMALL INFLUENCES

A gentle wind gathers the clouds, but still, no rain. Softer influences predominate as the power of the small accumulates. This is a time for smooth and friendly persuasion.

In the ebb and flow of events, there are always "low tides" - times when sweeping action is impossible or inappropriate, but when small matters can be attended to profitably, leading to bigger and better things later on. When the tide is rolling in, by all means, ride the wave; but when it is receding like it is now, focus on little things.

When the time is such that you cannot do much to affect large matters, persuasion and subtle influence can prepare the way for strength in the future. Use your intuition to chart your long-term course, but avoid bold actions for the moment - they are unlikely to work. This is an excellent time to refine existing abilities or develop new talents.

Be wary of others' intentions if they hold the upper hand in a situation. Examine their sources of power, so as to discover subtle influences you may be able to exert upon them.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>9</Index>
    <Notes>10 - TREADING CAREFULLY

People of ability find their way, and make progress even in difficult circumstances. Consider your steps carefully when you are surrounded by powerful forces. Weak and strong forces (or people) can co-exist when the weaker element does not impose upon the stronger, when the weaker maintains good humor and avoids taking bold action. When treading among sleeping tigers - or slippery stones - step gingerly; and don't stumble.

In the company of strong, brash people, rushing wildly ahead brings misfortune. Now is not a good time for taking the initiative; rather, try getting by with a little grace and good humor. In the court of a powerful king, the jester often has more power than the prince.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>10</Index>
    <Notes>11 - HARMONY

Earth stands above heaven and heaven seems to be on earth. The gravity of matter merges with the upward radiation of the light to merge in a deep harmony. This juxtaposition denotes a time of peace and blessings for all living things. In the affairs of men, tranquility comes when the good, strong and powerful show favor to the lowly, and those of more modest means are well disposed towards those who are currently blessed. There is an end to all feuds. In such a state, energy is high, the way clear, and the prospects for great success outstanding.

A deep chaos abides in nature, but man, by carefully responding to the rhythms and cycles of the world around him, can find peace in the natural world. By planting the right crop in the right place in the right season, the farmer brings harmony to the natural world of plants, and prosperity to his family. Similarly, any business must adjust to the natural cycles of the season; only through flexibility and adjustment can order and growth be maintained. Peace produces a time of flowering and prosperity; the wise person channels this positive energy to all quarters, to each in proper proportion, just as a farmer waters his field. But be vigilant: otherwise, peaceful conditions can foster the growth of weeds as well as flowers.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>11</Index>
    <Notes>12 - STANDSTILL

In a state of standstill and decline, confusion and disorder prevail. Inferior forces are on the rise, while the powers of clarity and creativity are on the decline. In such times, the wise take shelter in their own integrity and quietly remain faithful to their principles. Retreat from public activities and common exchanges until the times once again favor forthright action.

During periods of stagnation, inferior elements in society prevail. When the inmates are overrunning the asylum, summon up your fortitude, hide your worth and withdraw. Concentrate on your personal affairs with a quiet dignity, even if that means forfeiting short-term rewards.

Desiring to change a situation too quickly often creates extra conflict. By accepting hardship, while striving to maintain integrity, you are preparing for future growth. "A seed of prosperity is often hidden inside the husk of misfortune."

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>12</Index>
    <Notes>13 - FELLOWSHIP

Fellowship. When communal bonds unite a group of people, great success is possible. But such bonds can develop only when personal interests are subjugated to goals which carry in them the essential virtues of humanity. The broader the basis for action, the greater the good which can be achieved. And conversely, the greater the potential good, the more powerful the support behind it. A spirit of cooperation steadies the boat, but it helps to have a beautiful island to row towards.

Learn to respect the strength in diversity, for a community's true power lies not in its numbers, but in the diverse skills and resources of its members. Just as the stoutest walls are reinforced with many different materials, so the strongest groups allow differences to co-exist inside the whole.

With a unified group solidly behind you, even very difficult enterprises can be attempted without great risk.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>13</Index>
    <Notes>14 - AFFLUENCE

Supreme success! Like the proverbial pot of gold at the end of the rainbow, a person whose fortunes have turned for the better shines brightly. At the core of this success lies unselfishness and modesty, for it is the tendency of a flexible or yielding nature to bind powerful forces to it, particularly when prosperity begins to manifest. When power is wielded with grace and dignity, there is supreme success and great abundance!

Ah, but be careful. Along with any accumulation of wealth or influence may come an accumulation of pride and arrogance. Fight this tendency if you intend to continue prospering. Stay attentive enough to manage your affairs well. And remember that while material prosperity certainly beats the alternative, it is only one of many elements of a satisfying life.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>14</Index>
    <Notes>15 - HUMILITY

Humility is often rewarded in human affairs, just as valleys are filled by the erosion of great mountains. It is the way of the world to fill the empty cup. Regardless of your position, humility is a positive and deceptively powerful attribute. If you are in a high position but are still humble, people will be drawn to you and the causes you espouse. If your position is lowly, humility will endear you to those of higher status. True humility is a virtue to which all should aspire.

The most successful people are those who know how to bring each situation into balance by reducing that which is too great, and adding to that which is too little. Such a person craves not power, but balanced and stable relationships. Humility is the virtue which allows you to perceive the balancing force in each situation; humble people are not prey to the many illusions which grow out of self-importance. If humility is not natural to your disposition, make a conscious effort to develop a strain of self-effacing humor.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>15</Index>
    <Notes>16 - ENTHUSIASM

Enormous creative energy is unleashed by enthusiasm. This energy is like powerful music which inspires great numbers of people, loosening old constraints and generating new opportunities. Indeed, the power of enthusiasm is best symbolized by music and dance, for it is guided more by the heart than the head. Thus, great good fortune can follow when the leader of an enthusiastic group is a person of strong character, one able to guide this positive force toward a favorable destination.

Enthusiasm within a large group generates a special kind of electricity. When a crowd is "charged", the singer scales new heights, and life becomes its own reward. For who is not in awe of thunder? And who would fail to fill his or her lungs in the aftermath of a cleansing rain?

Arouse the passionate support of others, while adjusting your ideas and plans to suit their needs. In this way you can fill your sails with the mighty wind of popular support.

To arouse others, re-double your own dedication, and dare to create an environment which is free of tension. Take joy in your work. Harness the power of song and dance.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>16</Index>
    <Notes>17 - FOLLOWING

Following brings supreme success. You may not be able to change the direction of the wind, but by frequently adjusting your sails, you can arrive at your destination.

Those who would acquire a following must speak the language of their followers. Those who would be loved must become the imagined lover of their beloved. Those who would prosper must bend with the pressures of the world. In matters of principle, stand firm; in matters of style and taste, swim with the current.

In the affairs of humanity, change is constant, and old ideas are continually discarded in favor of new ones. Only by being adaptable to the demands of the time can a great leader emerge. Only by adjusting to changing circumstances can one prosper in the world of commerce. Remain flexible, and you will gain the confidence of those around you. Bend and you shall not break.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>17</Index>
    <Notes>18 - REPAIRING WHAT IS SPOILED

Something has been spoiled and it is time to repair the damage. In the world of human affairs, indulgence and corruption grow like weeds in an untended garden; they must be faced squarely, and rooted out through bold action. Eliminating corruption - and the sloppiness which often leads to corruption - is one of the most ennobling of all human enterprises, and can clear the way for fresh, new beginnings.

The time has come to become lean and efficient. The weeds must be rooted out now, before the whole garden is lost. Fighting decay, sloppiness and corruption is not a simple matter; all steps must be evaluated carefully, and planning must precede action. Resist the temptation to strike out prematurely. Gather strength behind you, and marshall your inner resources, because arresting decay is no simple matter. When you do act, make your strike as precise and clear as the path of the surgeon's knife.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>18</Index>
    <Notes>19 - APPROACHING OF SPRING

Spring is approaching. Good times ahead seems inevitable; there is vitality in the air. This is a most auspicious time. Like a snake emerging from hibernation, negative forces are only just beginning to stir, and can be effectively controlled. This is a time of hopeful progress, and must be used to best advantage. When approaching good fortune, conscientious work pays great dividends. A clear road lies ahead.

Act now, for at some point this ripe opportunity for advancement will be reversed. No spring lasts forever. It's always wise to stay alert and note the changing signs of the times.

Spring is always the season of new relationships. In the bounty of good times, new bonds are formed effortlessly. Relationships born in spring can serve well to warm the following autumn and winter.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>19</Index>
    <Notes>20 - OVERVIEW

Overview is a time for composure and contemplation. As a result of profound contemplation, a hidden force emanates from us, influencing others without their being aware of it. Do not underestimate the power of this force. Like the wind blowing across the tree tops, its presence is perceived through the effect it has on everything it touches.

Shallow wells rarely strike water, and shallow minds often come up empty. The ability to keep still and simply observe deepens resolve, and attracts good fortune. Discern the difference between what is deep and what is surface within yourself - and you will be able to distinguish between the two in the outer world as well.

During a period between events, the practice of stillness with awareness is a good idea. Only by observing and absorbing the true nature of things - by apprehending the rhythms and cycles which guide all creation - can we discover the laws which apply to our own individual lives. Examine yourself and the overall situation, not just with the thought of discovering truth, but with the idea of concentrating your personal power.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>20</Index>
    <Notes>21 - CUTTING THROUGH

The situation calls for confronting a tenacious knot and cutting through it. Somehow, the way to harmony and unity is blocked or frustrated - perhaps by a tangle of deceit or corruption. Like Alexander the Great cutting the Gordian knot, take decisive action and you will meet with good fortune. Don't be afraid to shake things up a bit. The ability to take corrective measures, when they are needed, is an essential trait of true leadership.

But those who bring discipline to bear must, above all, be honest - with others, and with themselves. Honesty is the hallmark of the strong and self-confident. The successful person masters the art of honesty much as a swordsman masters fencing. When lies, delusions and game-playing are getting in the way of teamwork, a swift sword of honest action, perhaps even punishment, must be wielded to protect one's integrity and values. Decisiveness with integrity at a time like this brings good fortune.

Though your actions be vigorous, they must not be hasty, severe, or arbitrary. Be sure to carefully consider all the circumstances. In the case of a serious disruption of relations or events, you must forgive, but not forget - at least until a person has made reparation for his mistakes. If corrective action is necessary, make certain that it fits the crime. When rules have become slack and useless, only through the institution of clear and swift penalties can their effectiveness be restored.

In situations where serious issues of justice are at stake, keep careful records, and do not hesitate to go public with the truth.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>21</Index>
    <Notes>22 - GRACE AND BEAUTY

A splashy sunset bathes the mountains in a soft radiance; the light of a full moon dances on the surface of a rippling river: Grace and beauty adorning the natural world. Grace is not an all-powerful force, nor is it the essential or fundamental thing. By itself, it is form without content. Grace is moonlight on water, not the sunlight at noon. Yet grace brings artistic expression into the world, and enhances the quality of our lives.

In the arts, grace arises out of adherence to form: the dancer becoming the form of the dance, the musician giving life to the form of a musical score, the painter becoming one with the brush and canvas. In human affairs, grace is also aligned with form - with mastery of aesthetic and cultural forms honed by time and honored by tradition. Through appreciation of graceful forms in human culture we apprehend the pure beauty of the ideal, of life raised above the mere struggle for survival.

Possession of grace, like the bearing of a beautiful gift to a wedding, can add stature to those in humble positions. Take care to lend grace and dignity to small matters, while giving the weight of deep and careful consideration to matters of greater consequence. Though it should not be confused with true substance, an artistic flair can take one far in this world.
</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>22</Index>
    <Notes>23 - SPLITTING APART

In every life, all is not what it seems. At this time, reality seems like a hall of mirrors. Intrigues are multiplying like summer flies, and there are rumors of discontent. It is the time of illusion, disintegration, distrust and deception.

When you find yourself trapped in a hall of mirrors, sometimes it is necessary to retrace your steps. Return to the familiar; take solace in what is firm and secure. There is no blame in holding back; indeed, it is your responsibility to keep your strength intact for the period of resurrection, which follows the period of disintegration as surely as dawn follows the night.

Discretion is the better part of valor - and good timing is very important too. Learn to choose the proper moments for action, thereby avoiding futile effort. Be particularly attentive at such a time as this for changes that signal a time to retreat.

In the realm of personal relations, discovering illusion is always painful, and confusing. When in the midst of such a period, it is wise to avoid undertaking any bold new moves, and it is especially important not to jump to conclusions too quickly.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>23</Index>
    <Notes>24 - RETURNING

There is a turning point which recharges you and eventually brings success. It is associated with a turning of darkness back towards the direction of the light, the winter solstice, the shortest day of the year, the day when darkness begins to decrease and the hours of daylight increase. It is the beginning of a turn-around; a time of letting go of the old and making way for the new; a time of new beginnings, and it starts with rest.

Don't move too fast. The new momentum is just beginning; the turn-around demands that your energy be recharged by adequate rest, so that your life-force will not be spent prematurely. This principle of hibernation, of allowing energy to renew itself and be strengthened by rest applies to many situations - recuperation after an illness, the slow return of trust after period of estrangement, the careful development of new relationships after a splitting apart of old ones.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>24</Index>
    <Notes>25 - INNOCENCE

Innocence implies a natural harmlessness, openness and pure intentions which are unsullied by ulterior motives. The state of innocence has less to do with age than attitude; innocence springs from a heart which remains open to joy and wonder. Innocence, when guided by a firm faith in what is right, brings supreme success. Naivete unanchored by an ability to discern right from wrong, on the other hand, brings misfortune.

The hallmark of innocence is a willingness to treat all creatures with compassion and respect.

Those who possess a pure heart are best guided by their instincts and intuition. Thinking too much severs links with the guidance of the heart: namely, a clear intuition and strong guiding instincts. Be wary of courses of action which require too much cleverness.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>25</Index>
    <Notes>26 - CONTAINMENT OF POTENTIAL

This points to the containment of great power - power that increases as it is wisely stewarded. Like a river which has been dammed, or a cooking pot with the lid on, holding and containing power produces enormous potential. During normal times, daily ritual and habit help keep life ordered and serene; but in times of great opportunity, the force of a powerful personality is required. Focused attention is required to channel this great potential and achieve supreme success.

With regard to what is on your mind, you have considerable reserves of energy and support to draw upon. This is the right time to nurture creativity by collecting and organizing your good ideas and plans. In this way, even great and difficult undertakings can be successful.

A hidden source of power for the great is the study of the past. The lives of wise and successful men and women are like treasures buried in the earth. Great good fortune comes to those who unearth these valuable treasures by applying the lessons of the ages to current events.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>26</Index>
    <Notes>27 - NOURISHMENT

Nourishment refers to much more than a healthy diet. It is the care-giving function. Eating properly implies care for oneself; providing healthy meals in the home is a sign of caring for the family. The writer of a great book or composer of an inspiring piece of music also provides nourishment - to humanity in general, by caring deeply about his or her work and offering the fruits of it to the world.

You can know people by observing what they choose to nourish in their own lives. Do they feed and develop their own bodies? Do they cultivate their spirits, their intellects, their moral values? Do they nourish and care for those around them? If so, to whom do they devote their energies? The most successful people are temperate in eating and drinking, thinking and dreaming. They strengthen the world by nurturing the higher nature in man.

Pay heed to your inner thoughts and impulses, ignoring thoughts which undermine a healthy and persevering attitude. A wise person is temperate in the consumption of food and drink, because to be otherwise only leads to discomfort; the fact that temporary pleasure may precede the discomfort does not influence the person of mature character. In the same way, be discriminating in your words and actions, lest a desire for temporary advantage lead you to cause pain for yourself or others. Enrich your own character and you will naturally nourish everyone around you.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>27</Index>
    <Notes>28 - EXCESSIVE PRESSURE

Something is out of balance. Some pressure is causing an imbalance and needs correcting. But, if the dam is about to burst, moving out of the way is the first key to success.

When a person in a sagging mine shaft feels the earth begin to tremble, it is a time for quick, instinctive action and nimble footwork. At a time like this, only extraordinary measures can bring success. When the roof is collapsing, run first, choose your destination later.

Extraordinary times bring out the best and worst in people. Natural disasters bring with them stories of great heroism - but also looting and rioting. When great weight is on the world, powerful moments present opportunities to make great gains. Everything is in a state of flux. One can either move in the direction of positive change and improvement or towards stagnation.

This may be the moment you have been waiting for. Although the current challenge may seem to be more than you can handle, remember that a flood reaches its highwater mark for only a few brief moments, and then begins to subside. Action must be taken now to ensure opportunities for success later on. You will never discover the true extent of your own abilities unless you, at least once in your life, dive into a crisis with complete abandon, dedicating every ounce of your energy, every fiber of your being, to the cause at hand.

Dare to win.
</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>28</Index>
    <Notes>29 - DANGEROUS DEPTHS

Exposure to danger brings good fortune to those who move beyond it. Like boaters passing through white-water rapids, those faced with serious challenges must remain alert; they must take all available precautions; and above all, must keep going forward so as to remove themselves from harm's way. Once the danger has passed, good fortune.

The positive side of danger is that it offers an excellent chance to cleanse the senses and strengthen the spirit. Surviving danger brings with it tremendous reinvigoration, and sharpens the eye and mind for future challenges.

It is reckless to court danger, but critical to inner development not to shrink from it either. Those who respond to danger most effectively are those who are able to establish an inner bubble of calm in the midst of the action. A calm center keeps one rooted in the moment, alert and focused. Courage at such times springs from focused attention, from a willingness to penetrate the moment of danger to its very core, so as to shape it and transform it.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>29</Index>
    <Notes>30 - CLINGING LIKE FIRE

Flames cling to their source of fuel in order to keep the fire burning. Likewise, in the human world, everything that radiates light or love is dependent upon something else. Through these dependencies we discover that everything is related, each thing to the other. Awareness of your own dependency on others is the key which unlocks the door to your true place in the world. No woman is an island.

Fire is also a symbol of liberation - crackling little molecules flying away from home. Paradoxically, by clinging to what is right and proper, we gain inner freedom.

Given perseverance on your part, this reading indicates success. In spite of challenges, cling to what is luminous in yourself, in others, and in life itself, never forsaking your belief in what is right. When events seem foreboding, or people seem oppressive, remember the good that has been and is yet to be. Holding to this idea is to cling to the power of the light, the force which enables inner darkness to be illuminated.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>30</Index>
    <Notes>31 - MUTUAL ATTRACTION

The attraction of opposites is a powerful and fundamental force. The image of this reading is that of the attraction between a young man and a young woman in the courtship stage. In response to the magnetic attraction between them, the masculine principle (the creative, outgoing) seizes the initiative and submits to the feminine (the receptive, sensitive). When the assertive is able to defer to the receptive, and when the receptive accepts responsibility and exercises quiet leadership, an exciting and profitable union is the result. This brings good fortune, for all success depends upon the effects of mutual attraction.

Consistency is important in matters of mutual attraction, for this is what separates courtship from seduction.

If you are by nature an instigator, it is good to take the initiative. But you must remain sensitive, and highly principled, and avoid the temptation to be manipulative. Let the power of mutual attraction pull you along. If you are the receptive one, keep your mind innocent and free of pride, so that you may remain open to good advice or helpful assistance. When your influence arises from innocence, a powerful magnetic force is at work for you.

Remaining open to the forces of attraction brings good fortune. Closing yourself to them heralds the death of the soul. Learn to yield to the natural tugs and pulls of the heart.
</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>31</Index>
    <Notes>32 - ENDURANCE

Endurance is fostered when inner constancy is coupled with external flexibility. Long-distance runners must adapt readily to changing conditions, while maintaining an inner determination and strength of purpose. Two trees growing near each other adapt to enhance each other's survival. A strong image of durability is a stable marriage of intimate partners striking a dynamic balance between involvement in the outside world and nourishment in the home.

True endurance is not based on rigidity, for endurance implies movement, not immobilization. Only by adapting to change can we can we stay in the race; but only by deepening our sense of purpose can we develop the fortitude to win it.

Continuity is achieved through movement, not by keeping still. That which has ceased to grow is close to death. Stay active, but allow yourself time to stay in touch with your innermost thoughts and feelings.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>32</Index>
    <Notes>33 - RETREAT

All worthy goals meet resistance of some kind. When negative forces predominate, a well-timed retreat is necessary in order to stay on the path to success. Tibetans know this.

Strategic retreat is not to be confused with escape or surrender. Successful retreat demands quick and nimble movement - taking up a new position before you are damaged severely by the current situation. You are not admitting defeat by such action, but simply increasing your options, and preserving your resources. Sometimes it is necessary to slow down, let go or move back temporarily in order to develop countermoves for the future. Timing is critical, as is positioning after realignment. Considerations of personal security are critical.

Periods of withdrawal or retreat call for cool-headedness. It is necessary to keep your wits about you. Attend to small details while allowing yourself time to contemplate the whole picture. Be creative; not all progress follows a straight line. Self-confidence is also essential; small setbacks can easily become defeats if we allow ourselves to become mired in self-doubt or self-pity.

Waves of progress are, by their nature, short-lived. Learn to attune yourself to the up-and-down cycles of life. When the wave is behind you, ride it in; when it's not, lie low. Don't fool yourself into thinking that you can "fix" any situation whenever you feel like it. Some things are bigger than you are. Hold your pride in check and you will be better prepared to find creative openings.</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>33</Index>
    <Notes>34 - GREAT VIGOR

Congratulations! There is strength and vigor in this situation - like a ram who has knocked down a fence to free himself from captivity. This points to a time when a strong force comes into its own and achieves power.

When a leader finally comes into power, his or her personal strength usually has peaked. Great strength has been required in climbing to the mountaintop, but once at the summit, the support of others is needed to maintain position. A shift in attitude becomes necessary. Raw strength must be tempered by wisdom; to maintain power, the strong leader must learn to give it away, to share it with others. Only then will his position be secure, for he will not only be the possessor of power, but the source of it as well.

If you find yourself in a powerful position, it is especially important to act responsibly and react with care. Power must not be allowed to degenerate into raw force which rides roughshod over everything in its path. A strong sense of responsibility to the collective good is the key to the successful exercise of power. By following what we intuitively know to be for the greater good, we avoid reckless abuses of power which in the end undermine the source of our strength. Arrogance contains the seeds of its own undoing.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>34</Index>
    <Notes>35 - EASY PROGRESS

The general situation is one of easy, natural progress. What has been weak is steadily ascending, and by gaining a prominent position, becomes more powerful. The image is the light of the rising sun, which at first appears dimly through the mists. But this weak light later radiates with powerful clarity once the sun has reached a high position in the sky.

Progress is made when those in subordinate positions make peace with those above, and in so doing create a natural means for their talents and abilities to become prominent. It is by recognizing and riding with the natural course of events- by hitching our wagon to the rising sun, as it were - that we advance our position and earn respect.

Don't forget, that goodness in human nature is like the dim but beautiful early morning light. It can easily be obscured - by greed, hatred and other forms of self-absorption - just as the morning light can be swallowed by fog. Be reminded that progress is achieved most effortlessly when right action is taken without concern for immediate reward, and when the path of the weaker aligns with that which is strong.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>35</Index>
    <Notes>36 - DARKENING OF THE LIGHT

When the light goes down, it may be wise to become invisible. The image is of fresh darkness, the period after the sun has gone down or the fire has gone out. There is still much activity left over from the light of day, and movements in the outer world are at their most dangerous. Even the smallest sound, the faintest glow of light, can attract unwanted attention.

When the darkness of stupidity reigns, it is best that your own brilliance stay "hidden under a bushel basket." That is, your thoughts and efforts should be quiet and self-contained, and protected, as much as possible, from harmful external influences.

Whatever you do, don't let yourself be swept along on the current of conventional wisdom when dangerous uncertainties exist. Try not to become too depressed or anxious; this period will pass. Just endure it for now and inwardly preserve your self-confidence, while outwardly remaining cooperative and flexible. The time to assert yourself will come. Avoid looking too far ahead if you have not yet achieved your goals. That only brings regret and longing, which can eat away at your inner resources.

Be cautious and reserved. Control yourself. Do not needlessly awaken dormant forces of opposition. During dark, unsettled periods, it is best to step gingerly around the sleeping dogs.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>36</Index>
    <Notes>37 - COMMUNITY

A family that works is one where healthy interdependence is supported. Leadership is essential, but strong kinship is dependent upon every member of the clan. Trust, shared responsibilities and good communication are essential. Each member must be encouraged to find his or her appropriate expression, and contribution.

The functional family is a team which symbolizes the ideal of human interdependence, and has long provided a firm foundation for society. The healthy family is a microcosm of society and the native soil in which ethical values take root and grow. Fertilize this soil, and the whole of society benefits.

The power which bonds a family together is the feminine principle - gentleness and receptivity. Relationships in all kinds of teams are improved through cultivation of this principle. Learn to accept both advice and aid from others, and be willing to assume an appropriate role in any group you join. A good team player is very valuable to others.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>37</Index>
    <Notes>38 - DIVERGING INTERESTS

An image of estrangement is indicated here. When brothers and sisters marry, they grow apart, since their allegiances now lie with new families. Though they will remain close enough to successfully deal with problems and share minor interests, they will be unable to undertake any great projects together. Simply put, when people grow apart - even for the most natural of reasons - their points of view, values and interests diverge.

Divergent natures and interests do bring opposition into the world of human affairs. And when opposition drifts into alienation and enmity, no good results. But when opposition takes the form of healthy competition, or when it is simply part of the natural order of things and is recognized as such, good fortune is possible.

Even when diverging energies make a situation seem stagnant or futile, remember: there are always creative possibilities inherent in polarities. One is reminded of the interplay of opposites that is fundamental for the creation of life itself. But when opposition has its roots in issues of principle, hold to your integrity and individuality. Avoid becoming involved with vulgar or base people who do not share your values. With both people and companies, one measure of stature is the quality of the competition.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>38</Index>
    <Notes>39 - TEMPORARY OBSTACLES

Have temporary obstacles been blocking your way? In the course of trying to reach a goal or fulfill a personal ambition, obstructions inevitably present themselves. This is not always a bad thing. Obstacles, difficulties and even setbacks which are eventually overcome often become assets. Without irritating grains of sand, oysters would never make pearls.

The obstacles pointed to here are not permanent, yet they are in the way. As when a large boulder falls in the road, the best course of action is usually to go around it, rather than to try to move it out of the way. Temporary obstacles must be seen for what they are - temporary - and should not be allowed to take on too much significance.

A positive aspect of even the most difficult obstacle is that it may cause a person to turn inward, and gain greater depth and character. While the ignorant bemoan their fate and seek to blame their problems on others, the wise seek the cause of the problem within themselves. Through this type of introspection, obstacles become a means for personal growth and self-discovery.

Without air resistance, no plane would ever fly.

If you are facing temporary obstacles, try not to be overly concerned. Obstacles are a part of achieving every goal and furthering every undertaking. Setbacks and reverses can affect morale, but keeping up your self-confidence in the face of obstacles is part of a successful solution to many of life's problems. Obstacles of short duration are best handled with a yielding attitude. Go around the rock, don't put your shoulder to it.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>39</Index>
    <Notes>40 - DELIVERANCE

After a thunderstorm, or any period of extreme tension, a period of new clarity and fresh opportunity follows. The storm has the effect of clearing the air and suddenly reducing atmospheric tension. Deliverance is at hand. In the wake of a storm on land, deliverance appears in the form of new color and life, which bursts forth in all the fields and flowers. In the wake of a storm at sea, deliverance takes the form of land itself.

In the field of human relations, the rain of forgiveness washes the human landscape clean after a period of enmity and error. Great clarity of purpose and renewed vigor can follow the healing of old wounds. But care must be taken not to re-open these old wounds by moving too quickly. In the same way, it is important to return to normalcy first before moving ahead with new plans after periods of stress.

Following the resolution of a difficult situation, your first priority, should be to return to normal conditions as quickly as possible. Breathe a sigh of relief, but don't relax completely. It would be a mistake to re-awaken the sleeping dogs of the immediate past before the new situation has crystallized. Look ahead. Attend to any residual matters that need resolution, and do so as quickly as possible. Make a clean sweep of the past, move deliberately, and the future will bring good fortune.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>40</Index>
    <Notes>41 - DECREASE

Increase and decrease are part of the natural cycle of life. As another good book puts it, "To every thing there is a season, and a time for every purpose under heaven." Like a reservoir that is being used to irrigate the fields, learning to accept a decrease in position or material possessions is part of preparing for increase in the future.

We may live in materialistic times, but there is no disgrace in material decrease, particularly if it represents an investment in future gain - even if that gain be in the form of learning or the development of personal character. Likewise, the inner strength that comes from bearing loss can be balanced by a corresponding increase in inner strength and insight. When letting go of material desires leads to a greater simplicity in daily life, good fortune often comes calling.

In nature, the lake evaporates to form the clouds that drop the rain which nurtures the surrounding forest. As the forest grows thick, more rain is captured for the lake. Similarly, an "evaporation" or decrease in one area of your life, may give rise to an eventual increase. A loss of responsibility at work can mean more free time; more free time may generate more career options. A decrease in material possessions can free the spirit and fill the soul.

Be mindful of the lesson of young lovers: even with a minimum of possessions, feelings of the heart can bring an unsurpassed richness to life. The smallest of actions, if sincere, have value. So remain confident, for a time of decrease may actually bode good fortune. Especially if you remain open to that possibility.

Let go of frustration, resistance and regret over whatever may be decreasing at this time. Accept the cycle.
</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>41</Index>
    <Notes>42 - INCREASE

Substantial progress and increasing prosperity is exhilirating, as long as you go with the flow while it lasts and keep the interests of others in mind. Like white water on a river, periods of increase are often of short duration; it furthers one, therefore, to shoot the rapids now, while the opportunity is there.

Leadership in times of opportunity involves commitment to the needs of one's cohorts or dependents. Only by realizing that to lead is to serve, can a leader fortify his or her position to bring about a lasting increase in prosperity. In a time of general increase, those who contribute most directly to the common good will achieve the greatest rewards.

When opportunities for increase arise, supreme good fortune comes to those who act swiftly and boldly, while avoiding the trap of letting their actions be merely self-serving. If you aspire to a position of prominence, the most enduring strategy is to work to raise the tide of your entire community or company, rather than to try to swim upstream on your own.

When the times favor prosperity, and when leadership is in the hands of the broad-minded, supreme good fortune results.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>42</Index>
    <Notes>43 - DETERMINATION

Personal resolution points to a breakthrough, but decisive action is necessary. As long as you diligently hold your ground and ward off negative tendencies or evil influences, the good will prevail.

The persistence of evil is a constant in human affairs; just when it is thought to have been eradicated, up it will pop again, sprouting through some crack in the pavement of decent society. Evil need not take extravagant, forms, such as those exhibited in Nazi Germany. Garden-variety lies and deceit are much more common and persistent, but should be rooted out just as diligently. One must be resolved against negativity - whether in one's social or professional life, or in one's own soul. In either case, definite rules must be followed for the struggle to succeed.

The first rule: do not compromise with evil. Negative actions must be identified openly for what they are, and discredited. The second: one cannot resist negativity on its own terms. New, positive alternatives which lead away from the source of the problem are generally more successful, and appropriate, than to counter negativity with raw power. The third rule: the means used to counter negativity must be consistent with the end to be achieved. One cannot stop the spreading of lies by spreading more of them.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>43</Index>
    <Notes>44 - LIAISON

The attraction is strong. But the relationship is not destined to last. Be careful - the coming together of disparate forces may not be what it seems. An apparently harmless, but potentially dangerous, element has attracted attention to itself and is pulling on a stronger one. One ancient image is of a bold but immature young girl who uses her charms to gain influence with a powerful man. The man dallies with her, thinking that it can do him no harm. Ha, famous last thoughts! When power shifts into the hands of those unprepared for it, harm comes to all parties.

Still, you need not fear meetings with those whose positions are widely different from your own, so long as you know you are free of ulterior motives.

Be especially wary of temptations which arise because of your position, or your connection to someone in an important position. Generally, it is best to combat such temptations by snipping them in the bud before they can flower. As soon as a dangerous liaison presents itself is the time to speak up. On the other hand, there are times when the meeting of the yielding and the strong turn out to have been opportunities for truly positive and constructive relationships. The difference between careless connection and a relationship of depth lies in the motives of the heart. How sincere are you?

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>44</Index>
    <Notes>45 - GATHERING TOGETHER

The power of gathering together is represented by a rally, where each individual's strength is magnified by the power of the community as a whole. History has shown that mass movements can bring about stable, ordered and durable conditions for the better. This reading may be pointing to an auspicious time for large undertakings. But the guiding force of a shared vision is essential to hold the forces of unity together, and keep them advancing toward a common goal.

Another image for this situation is that of a lake filling with water. Just as the fullness of the lake can bring good fortune to all in its sphere, it can also overflow, leading to calamity. Thus in a time of gathering together it is essential that precautions against unforeseen danger be considered along with efforts to advance along a clearly-charted course. Much of human misfortune comes from unexpected events for which we are ill prepared; when gathered together with others, we are both more powerful and, in some ways, more vulnerable.

Any time of unity is a time of potential greatness. But that greatness can be both positive and negative. Everything is magnified when masses of people unite for a single purpose. When many people unite behind a single goal or strong vision, it is wise to take personal precautions, and to protect your own reasonable self-interests, because these can easily be lost in the crowd.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>45</Index>
    <Notes>46 - PUSHING UPWARD

Advancement is represented by the forces of growth in springtime, when new plant life pushes upward through the earth's crust. The emphasis is on upward motion, from obscurity to influence, with growth fostered by adaptability and the absence of opposition. Constant, flexible growth is the key attribute of a plant pushing upwards. This reading suggests a period of promotion and prosperity in your life.

A wise person, in harmony with fate, is sensitive but determined. Make a sincere effort to apply resolute effort against the forces of inertia, and good fortune will follow. By remaining tolerant and flexible, you will be able to retain the kind of conscious innocence which fuels growth and advancement. Will power and self-control are necessary to manage this growth properly, but an inner enthusiasm for life is what nurtures it.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>46</Index>
    <Notes>47 - OPPRESSION

The image of oppression conjures up a dried up lake bed with nettlesome crows stalking the shoreline. Hard times shrivel our spirits, and give rise to a multitude of "crows" in the form of troublesome worries. Times of great loss or personal failure break weaker people; but the strong of heart can bend with fate. To endure hard times - or even grow and benefit from them - it is essential to tap that deepest stratum of personal identity, that which is deeper even than fate, and which is incorruptible by even the harshest realities. It is essential, in other words, to tap the wellspring of human endurance: hope.

In a sense, there is no such thing as failure. There is only sweet and sour reality, and more is learned from the sour, oftentimes, than from the sweet. For failure, hard as it may be to swallow, opens the blinds to the real world, and reawakens the clarity of vision known only to those who have risked, and tasted, disappointment.

When in the throes of hard times, it is essential to be resolute and strong on the inside while remaining quietly cheerful on the outside. Avoid too much talking - except to your closest friends. Your words will have little effect on all others, since your influence will be at a low ebb - and they will drain you of vital energy. Strong silence is the most skillful posture when facing the public during adversity; it shows that your inner core is strong enough to withstand the current troubles, and suggests that your recovery will be complete. At the same time, talking openly to those you trust is equally important, for in times of calamity, talking is part of healing.

Keep in mind that failure - the final taboo in modern society - is but one part of the inevitable cycle of life for those who dare to live fully and completely. Never to fail at all is to fail in the biggest way - avoiding risk altogether, one cannot help but fall far short of what might have been.

The Future of This Situation:

Because your hexagram for the situation or concern you're wondering about has changing lines, the Oracle has even more insight to give you. Changing Lines are the part of an I-Ching reading that always gives the most powerful advice about a situation because they represent the factors that are causing things to change right now.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>47</Index>
    <Notes>48 - THE WELL

Throughout various cultures and political systems of the world, the well has served as a universal symbol for that which sustains life and provides a constant, inexhaustible source of nourishment for mankind. For the life-force, in other words.

Like the well, human nature is the same around the world. The passage of time cannot add to its essential dimensions, nor take anything away. Still, just as a well can be deepened to produce clearer, cleaner water, so can we enrich our lives by delving deeply into our essential natures.

Beware of shallow thinking; like a little learning, it can be dangerous. The image of the well suggests that with depth comes clarity. Be patient, and penetrate both problems and your own nature to the core. If you do not lower your bucket to the depths, you're very likely to come up empty. When greater depth is desired, a lessening of speed is often required.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>48</Index>
    <Notes>49 - REVOLUTION

According to Chinese symbolism, the juxtaposed elements of this hexagram are fire under water. Fire evaporates water, and water puts out fire. Change often causes conflict; conflict brings about change. This hexagram refers to that time in the cycle of human affairs when things need stirring up, and when the hint of dramatic change is in the air.

In order to succeed, revolutions must be in alignment with certain immutable laws. They must begin at the right moment, gather support from a broad-base of people, be guided by sincere and capable leaders and - most important of all - must address a real need. The strength of the forces of change will always be in proportion to the urgency of the need being championed. This is true whether the revolution is in government, in business, in education or in one's personal affairs.

Revolutionary change points to a time when chaos arises from order. It is important to realize that not all order is good, not all chaos bad. Chaos, in fact, is an integral part of the way of things - as any parent (and modern science) will confirm. Have the courage to radically change and renew the way you present yourself. In this way, you can summon chaos to your cause, and you will unleash a new power on your behalf. If engaging in a negotiation, change the rules; if composing a piece of music, add the unexpected; if courting a lover, dare to be unconventional.

In periods of drought, even wild storms are preferable to yet another sunny day.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>49</Index>
    <Notes>50 - THE CAULDRON

The cauldron symbolizes nourishment and rejuvenation. Sooner or later, good comes to those who do good; joy comes to those who bring humor to others; opportunity comes to those who persist in their dreams. Rejuvenation is a returning to innate desires - and a re-charging of batteries through the fulfillment of these wishes. This reading suggests nourishment and transformation for people of goodwill. Great good fortune and success are indicated.

Healthy, regular sustenance is important, as symbolized by the cooking pot, which provides nourishment to all. When the cycle of humanity reaches its apex, each person's sustenance comes in the form of his or her deepest needs and desires.

Rejuvenation simply means that men and women of talent and insight are being properly nourished and valued. When society is functioning properly, such people are supported, and encouraged to contribute to their best abilities. A fresh approach to old habits is indicated in a period of rejuvenation. Look for ways of putting new life in old forms; for only when great vitality is present, can breakthroughs be achieved.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>50</Index>
    <Notes>51 - SHOCK

One hears thunder unexpectedly! First comes fear, then a sharpened, clearer vision. Recall a close brush with danger - a falling branch, an automobile accident barely avoided, an escape from a potentially violent confrontation. Such incidents first arouse every nerve fiber in your body in a brief wave of terror, but soon, once the danger has passed, give way to a heightened awareness of the world. The same process also occurs with other types of shock - the loss of a job, the death of a loved one, business failure and so on.

The lasting impact of a major shock can either be stimulating or debilitating, depending upon one's inner strength of character. The critical factor is the ability to become immune to fear, thereby transforming anxiety into a laser-sharp perception of the world around you.

When overtaken by crisis, the wise search their hearts for inner strengths, in order to face the world with courage. Courage often means daring to take the unexpected path - to bounce back quickly and self-confidently after failure, to have faith in the eternal when confronted with death.

We tend to think of shock only in the context of unpleasant events. We can also be jarred, however, by the sudden release of tension which comes with unexpected success. To keep your bearings in the aftershock of either trauma or victory, it is essential that your inner compass be aligned with "true north", that magnetic force which guides you toward fulfillment of both your deepest desire, and your highest destiny.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>51</Index>
    <Notes>52 - KEEPING STILL

Regular periods of keeping still are an important aspect of personal development and forward motion. The most restful person may not be the one who sleeps twelve hours a day, but the one able to grab catnaps while cruising at 500 miles-per-hour at 35,000 ft. Learning to act when it is time to act, and to keep still when it is time to keep still, is the key to obtaining the peace of mind which helps one stay focused when clear focus is needed.

Consider the spine, which serves as a switchboard for all the nerves of the body which mediate movement. When the spine is kept flexible and healthy through proper rest and relaxation, active movement can always be undertaken without strain. When the spine is held erect in a balanced sitting posture, the inner balancing of meditation can take place.

Treat your innate spark of vitality as if it were a candle in the wind - protecting it as though it were your only light in a dark forest on a moonless night. Avoid external conditions which threaten to snuff out the flame, and be careful not to suffocate it with your own ambitions and worries.

Time out. Relax, take your shoes off, and sit a spell. Let go of thinking. Meditate.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>52</Index>
    <Notes>53 - A STEADY PACE

Like an ancient old-growth forest - where the subtle play of light, texture and shadows is the product of a process measured in centuries and inches - most things of lasting value develop gradually, at their own pace. The ability to learn from experience - one of humanity's greatest treasures - implies constant yet gradual progress. The combination of stillness within and determination without are the essence of this condition. Good things sometimes sprout quickly; the truly delightful take much longer.

The principle of gradual development applies also to human relationships. For love, marriage and business relationships to endure, progress must be slow but steady: slow enough to allow for the bonds to knit properly; steady enough to move in the right direction.

You can't expect to have everything all at once. Development must be allowed to take its proper course; events must neither be rushed nor manipulated, but allowed to unfold in due course. In this way, you will come to enjoy long-lasting relationships, and achieve success in the world.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>53</Index>
    <Notes>54 - CAREFUL AFFECTION

Affection is the basis of all lasting relationships, but must be channeled properly in order to bring satisfaction and support the self-esteem of both parties. For example, a married person's lover would necessarily have conflicted feelings: affection coupled with insecurity. Relationships based mainly on personal attraction, especially those which are outside the mainstream, require special caution and tactful reserve.

If you assert yourself too much, or try to make yourself indispensable, you will only incur misfortune. It is never easier to make disastrous mistakes than when you venture outside the bounds of propriety. If you are in doubt as to whether you should follow your heart or your head, allow for some time to pass, and perhaps the answer will become clear. Initiating any action could bring misfortune. Do not attempt to be too creative or attract favorable attention at this time.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>54</Index>
    <Notes>55  -  GREAT ABUNDANCE

A time of abundance comes into full flower when the powers of a leader are at their peak. The situation is like that of the sun at midday - a high noon of clarity, insight and progress. Such peak periods can be brief. Whether this refers to a national cycle, a business boon or a period of personal abundance, it is important to bale your hay while the sun is shining.

During a period of abundance, it benefits one to show benevolence, to share the fruit of one's good fortune. Think of good deeds now as a hedge against times of scarcity in the future. This reading bodes well in the raising of children, and in the nurturing of a healthy family or any close-knit group.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>55</Index>
    <Notes>56 - THE WANDERER

A seasoned traveler knows that a special kind of decorum is called for when one ventures far from home. He or she must develop a yielding nature outwardly, so that the "local contact", or host, can open doors and prevent unseemly errors. But inwardly, the wanderer knows that it is sometimes impossible to discern the true intentions of strangers - are they hostile, or friendly, or merely opportunistic?

Any journey is ruled by the twin houses of mystery and discovery. Each new day is launched on a fresh landscape, one which reaches out to grab our full attention. Though travel is often a great teacher - and a great equalizer - there is a definite art to living with your home on the road. Increased caution and discernment become the keys not only to success, but to survival.

If you are entering a new environment of any sort - attempt to be sincere, flexible, and undemanding, rather than obstinate. You must jettison attitudes and habits which could encumber you, or make you overly conspicuous. The onset of a great journey is not a favorable time to enter into binding agreements, or to start new enterprises.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>56</Index>
    <Notes>57 - GENTLE PENETRATION

The general situation suggests a subtle penetration. Reeds bend softly in the wind, symbolizing flexibility and endurance. Here we see quiet, relaxed effectiveness in action. A gentle influence is at work, but just as the wind is ceaseless in its efforts, so too small forces can persist to produce lasting results.

Gentle penetration bodes well for new relationships. Just as a summer breeze slowly penetrates the woods to cool the forest, the ideas of gifted leaders slowly reach the minds and sink into the hearts of the people. In personal relationships, a gentle beginning is often linked to a long-lasting union.

When employing a force that is weak but persistent, careful aim is necessary, for only when a small force continually moves in the same direction can it have much effect. In human affairs, this kind of influence comes more through strength of character than by any direct confrontation or seduction. It's important to have, and stick to, clearly defined goals. Maintaining a strong vision and following a steady course of least resistance often brings good fortune.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>57</Index>
    <Notes>58 - JOY

A joy that is shared suggests a group of friends playing, or a carefree young girl singing to herself while engaged in her work. Happiness is rising within, and spreading out into the world!

Joy comes into the world through gentle means, but springs from a solid inner base. The power of pure joy should not be underestimated. The enjoyment of learning and discovery, for example, has been the source of much material progress. Accordingly, that which brings joy into the world is a source of considerable power.

If happiness is supported by personal stability, it will in time wear down the stiffest barrier and win over the hardest heart. True joy is a beacon in the world, and though it is indeed rare, its presence is an indication of great good fortune, both now and in the future. How could it be otherwise?

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>58</Index>
    <Notes>59  -  DISPERSING

Nothing survives forever, not even rocks, not even the most rigid of structures. The erosion of that which has been solid is not necessarily bad: it can mean that something new is being created. The image is of ice floes, hardened in winter, dispersing in the warmth of spring; when the ice melts, a mighty river emerges.

Rigidity in the hearts of men tends to breed a separateness which can only be thawed by a greater force: typically, some strong spiritual stirring. The thawing of cold hearts brings good fortune.

The first thing to dissolve is any internal rigidity which separates you from others. Try to work more closely with others, concentrating on common activities which evidence your integrity and native goodwill. Sudden, strong action in support of a greater good can lift the spirit, and lead toward new possibilities in many areas. Spiritual impulses - including righteous indignation and a strong sense of justice - should be honored, and acted upon. They can provide the initial impulse to important and constructive change.

And if you should have any lingering business or other partnerships which are inactive or not working, you might consider dissolving these as well.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>59</Index>
    <Notes>60 - LIMITS AND CONNECTIONS

Limits are necessary to give purpose and direction to life. Swimming in a sea of boundless opportunity would soon lead to exhaustion. Winging it alone in a sky of boundless opportunity would lead to being lost. In human affairs, the making of choices, and alliances, implies limitation, for in choosing one path another must be abandoned.

One key to a successful life is to select your limits consciously and carefully - to be discriminating in the setting of personal boundaries and knowing when to join in formation. Thrift, for example, often precedes prosperity; just as the letting go of selfish interests often leads to greater personal reward. Only by consciously accepting useful limits can one's energy be channeled to good purpose, and lead to lasting accomplishment.

Point yourself toward a middle way, the mean between discipline and freedom of spirit. Limits will come of their own accord; but to be able to consciously select your own affiliations in life - that's knowing how to fly! At the same time, do not go overboard on discipline. Even limitation must be limited, so that in attempting to bring order and direction into your life you do not choke off vital sources of enthusiasm and spontaneity.

Similarly, in groups and organizations, the rules and regulations should strike a balance between being too strict and too soft. If too strict, they build frustration among people, and ultimately become destructive. If too lenient, sloppiness becomes acceptable, and energy is soon dissipated. The best path is one which allows for the fulfillment of individual potential, while encouraging self-discipline and focus.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>60</Index>
    <Notes>61 - CENTERING IN TRUTH

Truth involves establishing an aware relationship between your inner core and the circumstances in your life. Centering in truth involves the ability to perceive a fundamental wisdom, reflected within yourself - and also in others.

Truth is transformed into power when you disperse all prejudice and make yourself receptive to the world as it really is. This power can be a remarkable force indeed - yet is rarer than generally imagined. It can be maintained only by cultivating a genuine openness to things as they are - a willingness to see, rather than merely look.

Whenever your inner life is clouded, your influence in the world is under a shadow. If you are fearful, you will be attacked; if you cloak genuine mysteries in dogma, opportunities for new insight will be lost. If you vacillate in upholding your principles, you will be tested. Yet, when you are firm and strong, the power of truth can break through even the most stubborn minds.

In any debate, the power to perceive the truth in the other side's argument is essential to achieving success. It is possible to influence even the most difficult people, or improve the most difficult circumstance, through the power of universal truth - for truth is something to which all things naturally respond. Get in touch with that part of yourself that is aware of this universal force of truth. Cultivate this inner resource, and you will become adept at using it to bind others to a common purpose.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>61</Index>
    <Notes>62 - ATTENTION TO DETAIL

Ambitious undertakings are not in order now, but attention to small matters brings progress. Such is the case of a person whose resources are meager, but who, through modesty and perseverance, rises to accomplish great things.

The key to success when the small potential dominates the large scene is to avoid pretentious ambitions and grandiose goals. The power of the small is served by slow and steady advancement, and succeeds through an honest awareness of its own limitations, without reservation.

Modesty stemming from recognizing your limitations is a fine quality, but it can be seen as weakness if it is not accompanied by conscientiousness. It is very important, therefore, to understand the demands of your situation, and not to expect success in big things right now. The wise person recognizes the nature of the time. So, know your own role, carefully attend to details and act with humility, and you can achieve success even with few resources.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>62</Index>
    <Notes>63 - AFTER COMPLETION

It is a fine irony that after completion of a project or great enterprise, there is still much left to do. Completion is merely a pause in the cycle of creation and decay, a momentary stillpoint for the swinging pendulum of life. Though completion does imply a period of restful pause - one which usually has been well-earned - it is not an actual end, but rather a uniquely harmonious flat spot in the constancy of change and movement.

The image of After Completion is that of a kettle of water boiling over a fire. When the forces are balanced, the water boils properly; but if the pot is too full, it may boil over and put out the fire; or, if the fire is too hot, it may evaporate all the water. In the equilibrium which follows the completion of an arduous task, the current forces must be watched carefully to assure that a proper balance is maintained.

After Completion is also the time for fine tuning, for refinements and embellishments of what has already been accomplished.

Even if we enjoy a rewarding situation at the moment, the laws of the natural world dictate that influence and success must eventually decline. Don't let current good fortunes prompt careless or relaxed attitudes. Whatever is successful or already established needs to be carefully tended and maintained, without trying to expand it. What is incomplete should be finished, and brought to fruition without delay.

Take satisfaction upon completion, but do not dwell on it. To do so brings a kind of completion to your own influence and capability.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
  <tblCardInfo>
    <Index>63</Index>
    <Notes>64 - NEARING COMPLETION

Your Present Hexagram

The situation is incomplete, but the chaos of the past is slowly giving way to order, and the goal is in sight. Nevertheless, you are still treading on thin ice - the way ahead is unobstructed, the goal is clear, but a cautious and careful attitude is still essential, lest you slip and fall.

Nearing Completion is the last hexagram of the I Ching. It suggests that the ever-spinning wheel of life never reaches an absolute conclusion. Just as a hidden sadness resides in the heart of true euphoria, just as the seeds of great achievement often sprout first in a caldron of adversity, so too no end is ever really complete without a new beginning stirring inside it. Though we divide life into categories in order to understand and master it, experience itself is seamless. With this reading, the 64-spoked, the timeless wheel of change is ready to spin onward, ever evolving, ever staying the same.

The situation represented by this reading can be compared to that of taking a lengthy trek over a high mountain. At some point before reaching the peak, you can see in detail exactly how much farther you must travel. You will have a good idea what it will take to reach the top, because of the climbing experience you've accumulated thus far. However, when you do reach the peak, which has been in sight for quite a long period of sustained effort, you will have done only that. You will have reached the top - achieving your initial goal - but now you must still descend the other side. This last critical segment is what remains before completion.

You may have little information and no experience of what it's like descending the other side of the mountain. All your attention may have been focused on the route up. The coming situation may seem very strange to you, unlike anything that you have experienced before. For the back side of the mountain is where all of the true mysteries reside. Proceed carefully, cautiously, alertly - and you will reach your goal.

</Notes>
    <NotesReversed />
  </tblCardInfo>
</NewDataSet>